A Guide to the Shackelford Family Papers 1920-1977
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Shackelford Family Papers 1920-1977
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3525-aj
This collection consists of ca. 500 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited by George Green Shackelford of Blacksburg, Virginia, on 19 July 1977.
Biographical/Historical Information
George G. Shackelford attended the University of Virginia and Columbia University; taught at Birmingham Southern College, Alabama; was a research fellow for the Virginia Historical Society, and is (1978) professor of History at Virginia Polytechnic and State University.
Scope and Content Information
This collection covers the period 1920 to 1977 and includes correspondence, financial and legal records, travel guides, magazines, newspaper clippings, postcards, speeches, and photographs. The correspondence and family records are primarily those of George Green Shackelford and his mother, Peachy Shackelford.
The Shackelford family resides in Orange, Virginia and traces its ancestry to Thomas Jefferson. Virginius Randolph Shackelford (1885-1949) married Peachy Gascoigne Lyne (1887-1976) on November 10, 1910. They had four sons: Virginius Randolph Shackelford (died an infant, 1911), Lyne Moncure Shackelford (b. 1914), Virginius Randolph Shackelford, Jr. (b. 1916), and George Green Shackelford (b. 1920). Other major correspondents include Elizabeth Shackelford (m. Lyne), Quincy Longstreet, Willie Carter, Jim Gum, Harriet Scott, and Grace Shackelford (m. George).
Organization
This collection is divided into two groups: Manuscripts, and printed material. Manuscripts include correspondence, speeches, and financial and legal matters. Newspaper clippings, travel guides, and magazine comprise printed material. Items within each group are arranged chronologically whenever possible. A small group of photographs and miscellaneous material is located at the end of the collection.
Contents List
- Manuscript Material
  - Correspondence: typescript re Civil War 1865 Feb 8 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: E.C. Godden to Miss Cassandra O. Moncure 1866 Dec 10, 1 ALS (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: primarily to George G. Shackelford and to Peachy Shackelford 1920-1977 and n.d. (Box 1)
    14 folders
  - Speeches and Lectures by George G. Shackelford and Virginius R. Dabney 1910-1952 (Box 2)
  - Deeds 1903-1906 (Box 2)
  - Financial Material 1923-1924, 1933, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - Genealogical Material re Shackelford Family 1952 (Box 2)
- Printed Material
  - Newspaper Clippings 1923-1976 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets, Travel Guides, etc. 1942, 1948, 1974, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Programs 1943, 1948-1949, 1954, 1974 (Box 2)
  - University of Virginia Student Directories 1941-1942, 1942-1943, 1947 Jan 1, 1947 Oct 1 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Shackelford Family Members n.d. (Box 2)
  - Life re Thomas Jefferson 1943 Apr 12 (Box 2)
  - Liberty re Thomas Jefferson 1943 (Box 2)
  - Deck Log Book n.d. (Box 2)